hello
all
全部的
you lovely people
尊敬的各位
and good morning afternoon or evening
早上好下午好或晚上好
depending upon where you're joining us from
根据你加入我们
my name is david
我的名字是大卫
amanda
阿曼达
and i'll be your host with mister kin russell as we
我将您的主机和亲属罗素先生为我们
kick off the eleventh year of our web g l and now web
启动web g l十一年,至现在web
g l and web g t u meet up event series on the agenda today
g l和web g p u见面今天事件系列提上议事日程
we will get the web
我们将网络
g l and web
g l和网络
g p web date followed by a great line up of seller speakers
g pu网络约会紧随其后的是一个伟大的卖方的宣传
with questions and answers at the end
最后,问题和答案
please make sure to put all your questions in the q
请确保将所有问你的问题
and a section below
下面一段
not the chat window
不是聊天窗口
so presenters can answer them before or during the
所以主持人可以回答之前或期间
q and a session
问答环节
this is being recorded and all will be available on
这是被记录和所有可用
the kronos website also send us an email at public
krnons的网站也在公共寄一封电子邮件
underscore web g l at prinos dot com
强调网络g l prinos点com
if you would like to present and share your web g l or
如果你想现在和分享你的web g l或
web g p
web g pu
work at a future meet up
在未来的工作满足
so without further ado
那么闲话少说
let's get started with mister ken russell
让我们开始与肯•罗素先生
our web g o working through chair for an update can
我们的web g l通过椅子更新可以工作
the florida years
佛罗里达州的年
thank you
谢谢你！
damon
hello
你好
everybody
每个人
let me get set up to share it
让我分享
okay
好吧
how we look at can you see my slides
我们如何看你能看见我的幻灯片吗
you can you're good to go
你可以好了
super
超级
okay
好吧
good morning afternoon or evening
早上好下午或晚上
everybody
每个人都
great to virtually see it all
大到几乎所有看到它
uh love to give you some updates on the web
想给你们看一些一些在网上更新
g l web
g p a p i s uh with my colleague kai minima
g p p s呃我同事kai最小值
who will give the one g p update
谁将提供g p u更新
so let's divert it
让我们把它
by the way
顺便说一下
all these slides will be available
所有这些幻灯片将可用
so don't worry about uh taking ex extreme amounts
所以不要担心哦采取极端的交货数量
of notes
的笔记
and by the way
顺便说一下
uh kai put a nice short link to these slides in the upper
恩凯把漂亮的短链接到这些幻灯片上
right corner
右角落
so first
首先
let me encourage you to please join the webgl and web
我鼓励你请加入webgl和网络
g p communities
g p u社区
both a p i s are supported by vibrant online communities
一个API受到活跃的在线社区的支持
and if you're working with these
如果你使用这些
a p
a p i
i would very much like to hear from you
我非常想听取来自你对建议
so on the web g l side
所以在webg l
please consider joining the webgl deadliest
请考虑加入webgl
their announcements of products
产品的公告
demos
演示
new tools
新工具
job hostings questions
工作主机的问题
discussions
讨论
everyone is welcome here
这里每个人都是受欢迎的
um uh damon already mentioned the public web geo mailing
嗯嗯达蒙已经提到了公共网络地理邮件
list
列表
the web geo matrix chat room also offers a great way
网络地理矩阵聊天室还提供了一个很好的方法
to talk directly with a browser implementers and
直接与浏览器实现者和交谈
other developers uh
其他开发人员哦
and you can find a lot of cool stuff release every day
你可以找到很多很酷的东西每天都发布
by searching for hashtag web g l on twitter
通过搜索网络g l在twitter上标签
on the web gpu side
web上的gpu
if you have feedback on the api and development
如果你有反馈api和开发
please see the main web gpu repository for options
请看到的主要web gpu存储库选项
on how to communicate your feedback to the community
如何表达你的反馈给社区
group
集团
the web g p matrix chat room also offers a way to talk
网络g pu矩阵聊天室也提供了一种方式说话
with browser implementers and other developers
浏览器的实现者和其他开发人员
and there's an increasing amount of cool stuff showing
有越来越多的很酷的东西
up on hashtag by gpu on twitter
在gpu在twitter上的标签
and we all look forward to hearing from you
我们都期待着你
so before we jump into the webgl and web g p specific
所以在我们跳进webgl和web g p具体
updates
更新
let me point out the release of k t x two
让我指出KTX 2的释放
which was actually ratified back in april twenty
这实际上是4月20再批准吗
twenty one
二十人
and we're trying to advertise it more to the corner's
我们试图做广告告诉更多人
community
社区
so this is a standardized image container format
这是一个标准化图像容器格式
for gpu textures
对gpu纹理
it supports all pixel formats and texture types
它支持所有像素格式和结构类型
a raise
提升
a cube maps and so forth
一个立方体地图等等
and has built in support for the basis universal codex
并建立了支持通用法典的基础
these are super compressed textures uh that are based
这些超级压缩纹理
on the gpu's native support for compressed textures
在gpu上的本机支持压缩纹理
um
嗯
but it's basically gives you the file size of jpegs
但这基本上是给你jpeg文件大小
with the the arab advantages of compressed textures
与阿拉伯压缩纹理的优点
there's a new extension to gltf called k h r texture
有一个新的扩展gltf称为k h r纹理
basis you
根据你
and that's what is adding this
这就是这个
ah
啊
the support for g p press textures
支持g p按纹理
multiple engines are already supporting this in
多个引擎已经支持这个
their own gltf loaders in three js babylon j s model
自己gltf threejs babylonj s模型
viewer
查看器
for example
例如
uh
there is a typescript parser library called k t x parse
有typescript解析器库称为k t x解析
you can use this with vinyl meals
您可以使用此与乙烯基餐
uh
container independent transcoders or with chronicles
容器独立转换器已经或记录
own transcoders that have been optimized for the
自己的转换器已经被优化
web and written in assembly scripts by
使用汇编编写的网页和脚本
uh
there is a reference c n c plus plus implementation
c n c + +有一个参考实现
for the k t x tools
k t x的工具
including precompiling command line tools that
包括预编译的命令行工具
let you take sources from pretty much any format and
让你从几乎任何类型的格式和来源
put them into the k t x container
把它们放进k t x容器
and you can even do this online with web assembly
甚至可以做这个在线web组件
there are some best practices and usage guidelines
有一些最佳实践和使用指南
out there
在那里
both for artists and for developers
为艺术家和开发商
you can see here some pretty oppressive results where
你可以看到一些漂亮的压迫的结果
uh the uh the model on the left is the original source
呃呃模型左边是原始来源
assets jpeg maintain
jpeg资产维护
ah
啊
the middle one is the um
中间一个是嗯
the highest quality universal a s t c plus e t c one s
最高的质量普遍t c + e t c一个年代
super compressed texture formats and the one on the
和一个超级压缩纹理格式
right is the lowest quality but highest compression
正确的质量但最高的压缩是最低的
e t c one s
you can see that there's like a factor of three uh reduction
你可以看到,有一个因素的三个减少哦
in the file size
的文件大小
and a huge factor
和一个巨大的因素
was it you know
这是你知道的
factor of six or something uh
六倍左右哦
reduction in the uh in the v ram required to store this
减少在v ram需要存储这个哦
model
模型
the models are are will be linked from this slide deck
模型是将从这个链接的幻灯片
in a minute
uh
but basically just by using the g l t f and k t x two pipelines
但基本上只是通过使用g l t f和k t x两个管道
you get tremendous reductions in size of your art
得到极大的减少你的艺术
assets
资产
so please check it out
所以请检查一下
ah
it's amazing
令人惊奇的
it works everywhere on the web
在网上到处都是
offline in native engines
离线在本地引擎
and it's a great way to uh reduce the size of your files
这是一个好办法哦减少文件的大小
and get amazing quality
并获得惊人的质量
okay
好吧
so jumping right into the brasserie implementary
所以跳,餐馆的实施
updates
更新
firefox has been working on miscellaneous performance
firefox一直致力于各种各样的性能
provements
研究
many of these are specifically targeted at google
其中很多是专门针对谷歌
needs background
需求背景
blurred and replace effects
模糊和替换的效果
which in case you didn't know
如果你不知道
we're actually built on top of web
我们实际上是建立在网络之上
and firefox is also working on implementations of
和火狐也努力的实现
new webgl extensions
新的 webgl 扩展
in safari and chrome
在safari和chrome
as you probably already know
正如您可能已经知道的
webgl two shipments apart fifteen last fall on both
webgl两批分开15去年秋天
macos and ios
macos和ios
it's running on top of metal on all recent mac and iphone
它是运行在顶部的金属在最近所有mac和iphone
hardware and operating systems
硬件和操作系统
and apple and google are actively contributing the
和苹果(apple)和谷歌(google)是积极的贡献
collaborating on the common substrate uh we're working
我们工作合作共同底物哦
in particular
特别是
and angles metal backends
和角度metal后端
which was originally contributed by queen
最初是由女王
here are some highlights of recent work.
下面是最近的一些亮点工作。
the safari team is rapidly diagnosing and fixing
safari团队快速诊断和修复
any regressions that have been reported compared
任何回归相比,已报告
to the open gl backend
opengl的后端
both in terms of correctness and performance
的正确性和性能
the safari teams also fixing webgl two performance
safari团队也修复webgl两个性能
failures uh actually both both teams are working
失败呃实际上两队都是工作
on this
在这
and one highlight is a major transform feedback bug
和一个亮点是一个主要的改变反馈错误
fixed by greg savarez google and kyle pittsburgh
固定由greg savarez谷歌和凯尔匹兹堡
apple
苹果
we are working on supporting dual gp
我们正在支持双重gp
we are fixing and user test cases like unity's html
我们正在解决和用户测试用例,如统一的html
five export path
五个出口路径
and we're working to switch chromes use angles metal
我们致力于开发chrmes使用metal
back end as well
后端也
now all you developers can now consider web g l two
现在所有你开发人员现在可以考虑web g l两个
universally available across browsers
普遍可用的跨浏览器
operating systems and devices
操作系统和设备
and as an application author
作为一个应用程序的作者
you can target web g o conference
你可以目标web g l会议
i wanna tell you that web g l two has resolved many corner
我想告诉你,web g l两个解决了许多角落
cases in the api and behavioral differences compared
病例的api和行为差异比较
to the combination of web gl one
web gl的组合
plus its many extensions
加上它的许多扩展
and we strongly encourage you to migrate web gl two
我们强烈建议您web gl2迁移
i would like to assert
我想坚持
and i believe that it's true that it's no longer necessary
我相信这是真的,它不再是必要的
to maintain a webgl one fallback path
维持一个webgl后备路径
unless you need to reach absolutely every device
除非你绝对需要达到每个设备
out there
在那里
in particular
特别是
older windows
较早的windows
machines and android devices
机器和android设备
so uh
please consider revising your your code bases and
请考虑修改你的代码基地和
your engines and upgrading them to support webgl
你的引擎和升级他们支持webgl
now if you're excited about the idea of uh running
现在如果你兴奋的想法哦
chrome's health ankles
chrome的健康脚踝
metal backgrounds and macros
metal背景和宏
you can test this today by launching it from the command
您可以测试今天推出了它从命令
line uh
线哦
and you can compare its behavior to the old older open
你可以比较老旧开放它的行为
g.l.back end here are the command lines to use again
g.l。后端这是命令行再次使用
these lines are
这些行
you don't need to to scribble these command lines
你不需要写下这些命令行
that you can basically just copy
你可以复制
paste them into your terminal
粘贴到您的终端
there are a few regressions still there uh
有一些回归仍然存在哦
for example
例如
low power and high performance gps selection is not
低功率和高绩效的gps选择不是
quite there uh
很有哦
but it will be within
但这将是在
i don't know a few weeks
我不知道几个星期
we think so
我们是这样认为的
please file any bugs that you find with the metal backend
请文件与金属的后端,你发现的任何bug
on angles issue tracker
在角度问题跟踪器
please file any bugs that you see in web g l safari fifteen
请文件任何bug,你看到在web g l safari十五岁
on the web kit issue tracker and for other browsers
网络上的设备问题跟踪器和其他浏览器
bugs
错误
please consult the page
请参考页面
how to get a webgl implementation
webgl实现怎么走吗
and you can file them there directly
你可以直接文件他们
uh
now a couple of uh mentions of new and upcoming word
现在几嗯提到新的和即将到来的词
gl extensions oea straw buffers index
gl扩展oea秸秆缓冲指数
this extension was specifically requested by the
这个扩展是特别要求的
three d formats working groups implement advanced
三维格式工作小组实施先进
materials more efficiently
材料更有效
and we're excited to tell you that this has actually
我们兴奋地告诉你,这实际上
been approved by the website or working group
被批准的网站或工作小组
after long last and it's coming to operators soon
经过长时间的到来很快运营商
you can test it in chrome canary today by turning on
你可以测试它在chrome金丝雀今天打开
web gel draft extensions and about flags
网络凝胶草案扩展和旗帜
and within a couple of days
并在几天之内
that will no longer be necessary
这将不再是必要的
uh turning on what jail draft extensions it is um
哦打开什么监狱草案扩展嗯
and it will come to all of chrome release channels
它将所有的chrome发布渠道
fairly soon
很快就
afterward
之后
uh and will hopefully comes all browsers again soon
嗯,希望很快再所有的浏览器
afterward
之后
the base vertex base instance extensions have also
基地顶点基地实例扩展也
been in development for a long time
在发展了很长一段时间
these can provide control over these parameters
这些可以提供控制参数
of these draw calls
这些draw 访问
the base vertex for index draw calls
基本顶点指数画调用
based instance
基于实例
for instance
例如
ones uh
it also works with the multi draw extension
它同样适用于多画扩展
these reduce cpu memory overhead
这些减少cpu的内存开销
in certain scenarios
在某些情况下
we've had discussions with developers online about
我们已经与开发商在线讨论
them
他们
if you
如果你
if you know that you need these parameters
如果你知道你需要这些参数
please try the prototypes of these in chrome
请尝试在chrome的原型
we would really appreciate your feedback to know
我们会非常感激你的反馈
that they're working as expected that they're providing
他们按预期工作,他们提供
the performance improvement that that you're looking
你正在寻找的性能改进
for um
为嗯
and these will comes all browsers after the the community
这将是所有浏览器后社区
approval
批准
looking for a second implementation and another
寻找第二个实现和另一个
browser than chrome of these um extensions
比chrome浏览器的扩展
and that's really the only thing that's holding back
这就是唯一的阻碍
but we would greatly appreciate uh and user validation
但是我们会非常感谢哦,用户验证
that these are uh are working correctly
这些是呃是正常工作
so uh
所以呃
please try them out if you know the item
请如果你知道项目
uh they're out there
哦他们
now uh
现在哦
i'd like to hand off to kinda mia uh to talk about what
我想交给有点mia呃谈论什么
g p
thank you
谢谢你！
ken
肯
hey
嘿
everyone
每一个人
good morning
早上好
good afternoon
下午好
um
嗯
i'll be talking about giving some updates on web g
我要讲一些更新的web g
p u
so just in case you're not aware uh
所以,以防你不知道哦
web g p u is an upcoming modern style graphics a p i for
web g p u p我即将到来的现代风格的图形API
the web
网络
so that's along the lines of vulcan directory twelve
这是十二个火神的目录
and metal uh
和metal哦
it uses a validated style with with things like pipeline
它使用一个验证风格与管道之类的东西
objects and buying groups that avoid draw time validation
对象和购买群体避免画时间验证
and simplify the logic of of the a.p.i.uh
a.p.i.uh和简化的逻辑
it also adds a lot of features compared with web gel
它还增加了很多功能与网络凝胶
like compute shader shader storage
像计算材质着色器存储
and it avoids global state
它避免了全局状态
which helps make the api user to use
这有助于使api用户使用
and it has many more of their improvements
和它有很多更多的改进
webb g p u is also a foundation for future features
wbb g p u也是未来功能的基础
uh like binders rate racing shader features um sort
哦像绑定率比赛材质特性
of whatever comes up in the native apis
无论出现在本地api
and we want to be able to expose across all across all
我们希望能够让所有所有
browsers and offering systems in the future
浏览器和提供系统在未来
webgpu is under development on github at the w3c
w3c webgpu github上正在发展中
so thank you to chronos for hosting us here at this
谢谢您为托管chronos我们在这里
cronos meet up
克洛诺斯见面
and we really appreciate it
我们真的很感激
so webgpu standardization continues and conformance
所以webgpu标准化和一致性
testing is in high gear
测试是高速的
first stand for the specification and conformance
首先代表规范和一致性
tests were aiming to reach a one point o in approximately
测试是为了达成一个点大约啊
q two of this year
问今年的两个
so within a couple of months
在几个月的时间
the shading language itself is under rapid standardization
着色语言本身正在快速标准化
development
发展
we've been working on feature completeness and a
我们一直致力于功能完整性和
lot of language refinements and ergonomics
很多语言细化和人体工程学
etc
等
you can find the spec at this link
你可以在这个链接找到规范
the api spec is driving toward one point oh
api规范推动向一个点哦
so we've been felt on this
所以我们一直觉得
it's been on development for a long time
已经发展了很长一段时间
uh
most of the areas of the spec are pretty solid
大部分地区的规范很坚实
uh
we're working on writing the spec
我们正在努力写作规范
a number of recent areas of focus include video and
许多最近的重点领域包括视频和
canvas
帆布
interop
互操作
color management
颜色管理
privacy and security
隐私和安全
et cetera
等等
and you can also find the spec online
你也可以在网上找到规范
next slide
下一张
please
请
so webgpu is available to try today in chrome firefox
所以webgpu可以尝试今天在chrome浏览器firefox
for local development
为当地的发展
i recommend that you touched the latest browser codes
我建议你接触最新的浏览器代码
to use chrome canary or firefox nightly with these
使用chrome金丝雀或firefox夜间与这些
options
选项
ah
啊
these two implementations are mostly interoperable
这两个主要是可互操作的实现
but not fully due to the fact that the spec is not stable
但并不是完全因为规范是不稳定的
yet
it's been changing
它已经改变
and so some changes have made it into one browser or
所以一些改变让它到一个浏览器或
the other
另一个
chrome in particular
特别是chrome
is running an origin trial
运行是一个起源审判吗
which allows you to publish web gpu apps directly
你可以直接发布web gpu应用
to end users
给终端用户
so this enables you to get a token for your website
这使您可以为您的网站获得一个令牌
that enables web g p u to an end user without the end
使网络g p u最终用户没有结束
user having to enable any flags
用户必须使任何flags
it's available on mac
它可以在mac
windows and chrome os and is running through chrome
通过chrome窗口和chrome操作系统和运行
one o one
一个一个啊
which ends in mid-may
在5月中旬结束
which leaves the stable channel in mid-may
5月中旬离开稳定的渠道
uh
please note that if you use the origin trial
请注意,如果您使用原点审判
it is breaking by designs
它是由设计打破的
so you must keep your content up today
所以你今天必须保持你的内容
we do rolling deprecations and breakages to keep
我们不支持和刀具磨损保持
to keep things up to date with the latest spec
为了保持更新最新的规范
you can find instructions in web dot debt
你可以在网络找到指示点债务
slash
削减
gpa
which i'll talk about later
我稍后再谈
chrome is aiming for one point of release around chrome
chrome的目标是发布的chrome
one o two or one o three
一两个或一个o三
this is not a hard guarantee
这不是一个很难保证
but this is this is our goal
但这是这是我们的目标
that is a roughly june.
这是一个大约6月。
and linux and android support should come soon after
和linux和android支持后不久
that
那
next slide, please.
请下一张。
so there are a number of resources out there for web
所以有很多的资源网络
gpu
so
one of them will be brain and jones'presentation
其中一个将大脑和琼斯'介绍
in this meet up on webgpu best practices
在这遇见webgpu最佳实践
there are a lot of articles out there
有很多的文章
so web gpu dot web dot depth slash
所以web gpu点网络点深度削减
includes a tutorial on getting started with web gpu
包括一个教程开始使用web gpu
as well as instructions on using the origin trial
以及说明使用原点审判
and there are a bunch of articles linked directly
还有一堆文章直接相关
from there
从那里
so i've not included them here um
所以我没有包括在这里
but i recommend checking it out
但是我建议检查出来
there are lots of samples for help to help you get started
有很多样品的帮助来帮助你开始
so we've got basic samples for first triangle up to
所以我们有基本样本第一个三角形
real world computing graphics techniques
现实世界计算机图形技术
examples uh
例子哦
brand and jones has a number of examples for for techniques
琼斯品牌和技术的例子有很多
like co clustered trading and metabolism
像公司集中交易和新陈代谢
and a full fledged game that puts together a lot of
和一个完整的游戏,让很多
different features
不同的特性
um
嗯
and there's also a shark shark shell has a demo
还有鲨鱼鲨鱼壳牌演示
deferred rendering in web gpu.
延迟渲染在web gpu。
including some nasty bug views
包括一些严重的错误观点
they show what goes on under the hood
他们到底发生了什么
next slide, please.
请下一张。
there are also a bunch of projects with web gpu backends
也有很多项目与web gpu的后端
well under development babylon j s three g s tensor
在babylonjs three js张量
float js and others have been working on web g p back
浮动js和其他人一直致力于网络g p
ends for years
结束了多年来
at this point
在这一点上
um
keeping up with development of the spec
跟上发展的规范
there's also w g p u and the ecosystem of rust based
还有w g p u和生锈的生态系统的基础
webgpu projects that use that library
webgpu项目使用这个库
which can target web gpu assembly
可目标web gpu组装吗
webgpu has a new shading language
webgpu新的着色语言
w g s l or wiggle
w g s l或摆动
and so we're there are also a number of resources for
所以我们也有大量的参考资料
ah software resources for compiling between different
啊编译不同的软件资源
shader ah shader languages um between from from wiggle
着色啊着色语言从之间摆动
and spear v to wiggle spear v h l s l and m s l
和摆动矛矛v h l s l和m s l
which we use for implementations
我们用来实现
uh metal shedding language
呃metal shader的语言
which we use for implementation
我们使用实施
this is good for uh taking an existing shitter
这是好惨哦把现有的
seeing what the wigs language looks like
看到WGSL语言是什么样子
it's you
是你
and it's useful for converting existing shaders
这是用于转换现有的着色器
either on the flyer ahead of time
提前在传单
uh
you can hook this up with g.l.s.link in order to compile
你可以钩基准线。为了编译链接
existing gl
现有的gl
all the way to wake up.
一直到醒来。
uh
呃
there are a number of implementation
有很多实现
so google's tint
所以谷歌的色彩
which is used for our implementation
用于我们的实现
and mizzle is naga
细雨是娜迦族
which is used for firefox implementation
用于firefox的实现
so check those out if you are looking for shader tools
所以看看那些如果你正在寻找着色器的工具
next slide
下一张
please
请
two contributions to web gpu are very welcome
两个贡献web gpu是非常受欢迎的
the api has been developed under development for
正在开发的api了
over five years
在五年内
now
um
we're very close to a one point o release
我们非常接近一个点o释放
but there's a lot more work to do after that um
但是还有很多工作要做,嗯
and there are still still a still a few things that
仍然还有一些事情
are under development for one point o
正在开发一个点啊
so please try out the a.p.i.file any issues that you
所以请尝试a.p.i。文件你的任何问题
run into with the a.p.i.uh file feature requests
遇到a.p.i。嗯文件特性请求
if there are major areas that you would need in order
如果有主要领域,你需要在秩序
to port applications
端口的应用
for example
例如
uh file browser bugs against the browsers
嗯对浏览器文件浏览器的bug
if you find them
如果你发现他们
and try out web gpu via various libraries that have
并尝试通过各种图书馆网络gpu
web gpu backends try out the origin
web gpu后端尝试原点
try out uh publishing sites with the origin trial
尝试呃发布网站的起源审判
so you can get user feedback
所以你可以得到用户的反馈
um we're also under were were the conformance tests
嗯下我们也都是一致性测试
are under development on github
正在研制的github上
so you can also help with ensuring that our implementations
所以你也可以帮助确保我们实现
are consistent
是一致的
and of course
当然
contributing samples in demos using web gpu would
造成样本演示使用web gpu
benefit the whole community greatly
大大造福整个社区
you can join the conversations on the matrix chat
你可以加入矩阵上的谈话聊天
uh
that's a irc like chat room that has all of the web gpu
这是一个irc聊天室一样,所有的web gpu
developers and implementers present um
开发人员和实现者嗯
so it's a really great resource to get involved
这是一个很好的资源参与
next slide, please.
请下一张。
so today
所以今天
we have a great line up of presenters
我们有一个伟大的演讲者
i think i've already been announced
我想我已经宣布
but here's the uh
但是这里的哦
here's the the the list
这是列表
uh next up
嗯接下来
we'll be bringing jones from google
我们会把谷歌的琼斯带来
giving a presentation web g p best practices in demos
演讲web g p演示的最佳实践
then we have a video from takahiro ang yagi from mozilla
然后我们有一个视频从mozilla孝宏和八木
on his online ups editor for for the wakeful shading
在他的在线ups编辑醒着的阴影
language
语言
and then jonathan sanchez will talk about code vendor
然后乔纳森·桑切斯将讨论供应商代码
and donald hutchins will talk about new rendering
和唐纳德•哈钦斯将讨论新的呈现
features in play canvas
特性在画布上
as i think we've already mentioned
我认为我们已经提到过
but just for anybody who joined late
但只是为了谁加入了迟了
feel free to type your questions in the q and a at any
随意输入你在q和在任何的问题
time
时间
we will visit those at the end
最后我们将访问
and some of us might answer questions during the presentations
和我们中的一些人可能在演讲回答问题
as well
也
um
and just make sure to put the questions in the q and
一定要把在问的问题
a so that we have them in the in the question list at
所以我们在问题列表中
the end
um
and with that
和,
i'll hand it over to brandon
我将其移交给布兰登
all right
好吧
thank you very much
非常感谢你
kay and ken
凯和肯
i'm going to shorten my screen
我想缩短我的屏幕上
really quit
好的
okay, hopefully, everyone can see this.
好吧,希望每个人都可以看到这个。
keep looking good.
可以看到吧
great, thank you, alright. so.
太好了,谢谢你,好吧。所以。
pleasure to be here
高兴来到这里
everyone
每一个人
my name's brandon jones
我的名字叫布兰登·琼斯
i'm really excited to be able to present today
我很兴奋能够今天
going over some best practices for web g p u um
要在web g p u嗯一些最佳实践
so as for me
所以对我来说
i'm a developer on the chrome team
我是一个chrome开发团队的开发人员
i've been at google for about nine years
我已经在谷歌大约九年了
uh
currently working on web g p u as one of the spectators
目前从事web g p u的观众
along with kai
随着凯
and also a chrome's implementation
还有一个chrome的实现
and previously i worked on web x r and web gl as well
和我以前做web x r和web gl
so kind of just all things graphics on the
所以的一切图形上
and i like to build demos with the text that i'm helping
我喜欢用我帮助的文字来做演示
implement because one it's fun and two
因为一个很有趣和两个实现
it helps uh find bugs such how best practices provides
它有助于嗯发现bug这些最佳实践如何提供
good community resources since i just find it to be
好的社区资源,因为我只是找到它
in all around useful exercise um
在所有有用的练习哦
so i'm not going to go through all of these lane
所以我不会去通过所有这些车道
but um
some of the demos that i've done with web g.p.u.specifically
一些与web g.p.u.具体的演示我所做的
in the past have been implementing algorithms like
在过去已经实现算法
plastered shading or a implementation of generating
上生成的阴影或实现
marching cubes metabolism on the gpu
游行立方体在gpu的新陈代谢
which turns out is way way faster than doing it in javascrip
这证明javascrip方式比方法
uh
and then the one that i will display is my most recent
然后我将显示是我的最近的
is a game that i called cookie ball
是一个游戏,我叫饼干球吗
it was released around halloween
它被释放在万圣节
if you couldn't tell
如果你不能告诉
and this is a fairly simple game mechanics wise
这是一个相当简单的游戏机制明智
it is basically just break out um and everything is
它基本上是打破嗯,一切都是
just nice and scrutiny themed um
好,审查主题嗯
but it's also possibly the first fully web g p u game
但它也可能是第一个完全网络g p u游戏
uh developed um could be wrong about that
发达嗯嗯可能是错的
but it's definitely one of the first
但它肯定是第一个
and this was an exercise for me to just say
这是一个锻炼我只是说
you know
你知道
can we pull this all together and produce a a full playable
我们可以把这个放在一起并产生一个完整的可玩的吗
product
产品
make sure that we're getting some of the more common
确保我们的一些比较常见的
graphics techniques in there
图形技术在里面
you can see we're using shadow mapping
你可以看到我们使用阴影映射
we've got a bloom filter for any missive materials
我们有任何信件的布隆过滤器的材料
uh we're loading up g l t f uh assets
嗯我们装载g l t f呃资产
we've got some animation going in here
在这里我们有一些动画
it's all fairly subtle
这都是相当微妙的
but uh
但是呃
you know
你知道
just basically trying to pull it all together and
只是想拉在一起,
see what's difficult
看看有什么困难
what's easy
什么是容易的
what maybe needs some more work
也许需要一些更多的工作
what bugs we run into that kind of thing
什么错误我们遇到这样的事情
uh
so you can play this right now spooky ball dot com um
现在你可以玩这个幽灵球。com嗯
by the way
顺便说一下
these slides are going to be available
这些幻灯片是可用的
so you don't need to run around and
所以你不需要到处跑
and take notes like crazy because i'm gonna go through
疯狂地做笔记,因为我要通过
this kind of fast um
这种快速嗯
and again
一次又一次
a lot of you would probably not trigger gpu
你们很多人可能不会触发gpu
so that's far
这是远
and so some of this will sound like goblin google
所以这将听起来像妖精谷歌
that's okay
没关系
you can come back after you've tried it a little bit
你可以回来在你尝试一下
and are more familiar with the api
而且更熟悉的api
and you'll be able to understand a little bit better
,你就能更好地理解一点
what some of these are referring to
这些指的是什么
first off
首先
one of the things that i cannot recommend enough is
的一件事我不能推荐够了
to use the labels mechanism that we've developed
使用标签机制,我们开发了
everywhere uh every single object in web g p u has a
到处哦每个对象在网络g p u
label that you can set either creation time or during
标签,您可以设置创建时间或期间
the um during run time
嗯在运行时间
and you should do it as much as possible
你应该尽可能多地做这件事
there's basically zero runtime cost
基本上是零运行成本
and it will make your debugging life much
,它会使你的调试的生活
much easier uh
更容易哦
specifically because uh we is the web g l implementer
因为我们是网络g l实现者
or the web g.p.u.implementers
或web g.p.u.实现者
excuse me
对不起
we'll make sure to return the labels to you in error
我们要确保返回你的标签错误
messages
消息
so you can see an example at the bottom of this slide
所以你可以看到这张幻灯片底部的一个例子
uh
where we're saying
我们说
hey
like you try to write too much data into a buffer
像你想太多的数据写入缓冲区
and i'm we're actually returning the name of the buffer
我我们返回缓冲区的名称
that this error occurred against because as the the
这对因为错误发生
label gave us
标签给我们
and that makes debugging way easier
并使调试方式更容易
similarly
类似的
we also have a mechanism called feedback groups
我们也有一种机制称为反馈组
and you should use these uh wherever it's appropriate
你应该使用这些呃在适当的地方
this is really just a stack of labels uh that you can
这只是一堆标签哦,你可以
push and pop as you go into your command decoder and
推动和流行当你进入译码器和命令
the various render passes
各种渲染通道
and it just kind of lets us know where you are in your
它只是让我们知道你在哪里
your application
您的应用程序
so that once again
所以,再一次
when we generate error messages
当我们生成的错误消息
we can return the feedback group stack to you and say
我们可以返回反馈组堆栈你和说
this is where you told us you were in your algorithm
这就是你告诉我们你的算法
so that you can pinpoint where the errors happen better
这样你可以更好地定位错误的发生
ah
very
very valuable when you're trying to suss out where
非常有价值,当你试图弄清楚
it issue is
它的问题是
uh
turning more to the mechanics of the a p
将更多的力学p
i like the the getting assets in and out
我喜欢获得资产
um
one of the common uh patterns that we saw with web g
一个常见的呃模式,我们看到网络g
l was when you want to load an image from a j.peg or p
l是当你想要加载一个图像从j.gp
and g
和g
you would put it into an image tag and then push push
你会把它放到一个图像标记,然后推动推动
that image gentleman into text image two d
绅士形象在文本图像两个d
and that would be how you got a texture
那就是你如何有一个纹理
this is a very common pattern
这是一个非常常见的模式
we see it on all the major libraries
我们看到在所有主要的库
it's been happening since the day that what g l existed
从那天起开始发生,什么g l存在
or first existed um
或存在嗯
but you can't quite do that in web g p u
但你不能完全用web g p u
so my time is as a bit of a surprise
所以我的时间是有点奇怪
instead
而不是
you have to pass in image bit maps
你必须通过在图像地图
now you can get an image bit map from an image element
现在你可以得到一个图像的位图的图像元素
but we don't recommend you do that at least in chrome
但是我们不建议你这样做至少在chrome
it turns out that
事实证明,
that forces the decode of the image they happen on
迫使图像的解码他们发生
the main thread
主线程
and so you'll get a bit of a
所以你会得到的
instead
而不是
what we recommend is
我们推荐的是
ah
啊
anytime you're getting an image from like a u r l
当你得到一个图像从像u r l
just use batch to get it and get a blob out of that and
用批处理来得到它,并得到一个blob
what you can create image payment upon the blog
你可以支付在博客创建图像
this allows it to the code off the main threat
这允许它的代码的主要威胁
and so it's probably the most efficient way to get
所以它可能是最有效的办法
an image or a texture out of a j.peg or a phg
一个图像或一个纹理的j。挂钩或phg
however
uh
we really
really
真的希望你可以使用压缩纹理
really can prefer that you use compressed textures
而不是
instead
啊
ah
这是可以提到很多关于
this is something that that can mention a lot about
我要喋喋不休
and i'm gonna harp on
更因为它很重要
it's more because it's important
呃webgl没有船最好的压缩纹理
uh webgl didn't ship with the best compressed texture
商店任一
store either
支持小片状
support was little flaky
那里的工具并不完全
the tooling wasn't quite there
所以它没有得到那么多的吸收
and so it didn't get quite as much uptake as we would
有喜欢
have liked
但与g p u
but with what g p u
我们真的想要摆脱一个更好的脚本压缩
we really wanna get off on a better foot uh compressed
结构支持将从第一天起
texture support is going to be there from day one
uh
这是需要你支持每一个系统
it's required to be supported on every system you'll
嗯一个或两个呃压缩纹理格式
get um either one or two uh compressed texture formats
至少在每个设备
at minimum on every device um
有很多更好的工具
and there's a lot of better tooling in this
现在的生态系统
the ecosystem now
比如可以提到k t x 2的基础上普遍的东西
such as as can mention k t x two basis universal stuff
像这样
like that
这需要更多的代码
now this does take more code
uh
这不是完全可以代表
it's not something that can be represented fully
等一个幻灯片嗯的最后一件事
on a slide like the last thing um
但它是值得的
but it is worth it uh
会有
and there's going to be
我我肯定会支持所有主要的库
i i'm sure all the major libraries are going to support
它门
it out the gate
然后我有独立的图书馆
and then i've got standalone library
一个独立的库在底部
a standalone library down at the bottom here that
您可以自由使用或引用或任何你
you are free to use or reference or whatever you'd
就像
like
um
做最正确的事情喜欢解码了吗
does most of the right things like decoding off on
一个工作线程
a worker thread uh
是非常值得和演示
and it is really worth the effort and to demonstrate
我想做一个快速的案例研究的资产
that i wanted to do a quick case study with one of assets
从幽灵球我刚才演示
from the spooky ball demo that i just showed
这是明
this is the paddle
太小幽灵啊跟随和浮动
it's too little ghost that ah float with a cough and
来回
back and forth
不是很复杂
not terribly complicated
嗯
um
资产本身有五个纹理烤进去哦
the asset itself has five textures baked into it uh
他们都是p和g的
they're all p and g's
他们呃两个k由两个k h
and they're uh two k by two k h
这是荒谬的空间需要吗
which is ridiculous for the amount of space this takes
在屏幕上了
up on the screen
但我们会
but we'll
这出来的blender在大约12个字节
this comes out of blender at about twelve megabytes
这并不是可怕的
which isn't terrible
但可能是更好的
but could be better
um
在我的例子中
in my case
我使用一个工具,称为g l t f变换
i use a tool called g l t f transform
有很好的命令行接口
which has really nice command line interface
但也有一个库
but also has a library
如果你想做更多的编程方式
if you want to do it more programmatically
我用它来把所有g l t f跟踪资产和做
and i use that to take all my g l t f track assets and do
纹理编码与k h r结构基础
texture encoding on them with the k h r texture basis
你扩展养犬早些时候提到
you extension the kennel was mentioning earlier
这需要特定资产低于几乎
and this takes this particular asset down from almost
12个字节到一点七
twelve megabytes to one point seven
这是
that is
巨大的减少哦
huge reduction uh
这只是因为材质本身的一部分
part of that is just because the textures themselves
是如此的简单
are so simple
但就像我看到这种风格的减少在每个资产
but like i see this style of reduction on every asset
我上运行这些工具
i run these these tools on
而且
and furthermore
有很多其他相同的转换工具
there's a lot of other transforms that that same tool
可以做哦
can do um
如应用德拉高质量压缩
such as applying drago mass compression more
如果我叠在一起
and if i stack them all up together
包括调整纹理
including resizing the texture
所以他们不是非常巨大
so they're not so ridiculously huge
的资产,我船幽灵球
the asset that i actually ship in spooky ball comes
半杂志
out to about half a mag
就像小于百分之五的原始
which is like less than five percent of the original
大小
size
和大部分是从纹理压缩
and most of that is from texture compression
所以我不能强调如何宝贵的纹理压缩
so i cannot stress enough how valuable texture compression
is
我希望每一个人去使用这个技术想法
and i want everybody to use it
从第一天开始。
from day one.
从纹理
moving on from textures
的一件事我们gpu的介绍
one of the things that we've gpu introduces that's
不同于webgl有很多
different from webgl is there happens to be a lot of
方法数据缓冲区
ways to get data to buffer
顶点缓冲区
vertex buffers
索引缓冲区
index buffers
存储缓冲区
storage buffers
不管哦
whatever uh
这可能有点吓人
and it can be a little intimidating
但有便利函数对自助餐
but there is convenience function called right buffet
当有疑问
and when in doubt
这是从来没有错误的答案
that is never ever the wrong answer
现在你可能认为自己是便利功能
now you might think to yourself as convenience functions
因此
so therefore
它必须有一个缺点
it must have a downside
和我很高兴在这个特殊的案例
and i'm happy to report in this particular case
no
不是嗯
not really um
可能有情况你可以构造
there are probably scenarios where you could construct
一个更好的上传管道为一个特定的场景
a better upload pipeline for a specific scenario
使用一些其他的机制
using some of the other mechanisms
但实际上
but really
你应该下降
you should fall
你应该先试着正确的缓冲区,只走过去
you should try right buffer first and only go past
如果你发现这是一个瓶颈
that if you find that it's a bottleneck
特别是在使用类似的情况
and especially in the case of using something like
网络大会
web assembly
对缓冲实际上是首选方法,因为
right buffer is actually the preferred way because
它避免了一个不同的和额外的副本
it avoids a different and additional copy
这是其中的一个例子,使用方便
so this is one of those cases where using the convenience
函数是绝对
function is absolutely
um.
现在的另一个你要的东西
now one of the other things that you're going to be
处理很多web v p u是所谓的管道
dealing with a lot in web v p u is what's called pipelines
这是一大捆的所有状态
this is kind of just a big bundle of all of the state
你曾经是设置在全球1 g p或
that you used to be setting globally in one g p not or
和webg l
one g l
并不是所有的状态
not all of the state
but most of it things like shaders and blend modes
和多边形拓扑和所有这些东西
and polygon topology and all that kind of stuff
你会创造很多
you're gonna create a lot of them
呃
uh
现在有一种同步和异步版本
now there is a synchronous and an asynchronous version
这些函数的
of these functions
啊因为同步是一种空气引号
ah synchronous is kind of an air quotes here because
两个版本将立即返回给你
both versions will return to you immediately
呃
uh
然后在后台工作
and then do work in the background
但是缺点与同步版本
but the downside with the synchronous version is
它将给你一个处理管道
it will hand you a handle to the pipeline
你可以转身立即使用它
and you can turn around and use it immediately to either
渲染或调度计算
render or dispatch compute
如果你这样做
and if you do that
你的用户会看到大量喝他们的表现
your users will see a massive drink in their performance
因为机会是管道还没有准备好使用
because chances are the pipeline is not ready to use
除非它是
unless it was
和。
and.
你
you
你的g p u将你派遣
your g p u will hit that point where you've dispatched
工作,就停下来等待管道
work to it and just stop and wait for the pipeline to
完成编译材质
finish compiling shader
无论它之前需要做可以继续
whatever else it needs to do before it can continue
这可能看起来像一千五百毫秒
this will probably look like a five hundred millisecond
垃圾给用户
junk to a user
根据管道的复杂性
depending on the complexity of the pipeline
而不是
instead
如果你能喜欢
if you can like
说
say
在负载的屏幕上,你不需要
during the load screen where you're not needing to
使用管道
use the pipeline
相同的框架创建
the same frame that was created
您应该使用这些因为我认为版本
you should use the i think version of these because
他们会保证结果返回给管道
they'll return promise that results to the pipeline
当承诺解决
and when that promise resolves
管道是保证可以使用
the pipeline is guaranteed to be ready to use without
过度的停顿
undue stalling
所以你可以转身立即使用它
so you can turn around and use it immediately
你不应该得到接近相同的类型
and you should not get anywhere near the same type
杰克,你将和其他
of jake that you would with the other
嗯。
um.
夫妇的最后哦去这里的最佳实践
couple of last uh best practices to go over here
对不起
excuse me
关于管道嗯
regarding pipelines um
我们有一个机制被称为隐式管道布局
is we have a mechanism called implicit pipeline layouts
嗯。
um.
至少在那一刻
at least at the moment
我们还讨论这一点
we're still discussing this one a little bit
这是另一个方便的机制
and this is another convenience mechanism
但与正确的缓冲
but unlike right buffer
这是你应该小心的方法之一
it's one that you should approach with caution
呃
uh
隐式管道布局很好当你
implicit pipeline layouts are really nice when you're
做一个完全隔离的材质
doing a shader that is completely isolated
不与任何其他分享数据
it doesn't really share data with anything else
这是罕见的
which is rare
不可否认
admittedly
嗯
um
但是你可以说
but then you can just say
哦
oh
我想要你编译材质,给
i want to have you compile the shader and just give
我为我所有的布局哦买组信息
me a layout for all of my uh buying group information
这是缓冲区
which is buffers
纹理
textures
取样器
samplers
东西只是生成对我哦,
stuff like that just generate that for me uh and it
作品
works
它很有效
and it works fairly well
嗯
um
但是有缺点
but there's downsides to it
呃
uh
最大的一个是你不能分享购买
the biggest one is you can't actually share buying
您创建的组对隐式管道
groups that you create against the implicit pipeline
布局与其他管道
layout with any other pipelines
这不利于性能
which is bad for performance
然后另一件事
and then the other thing
啊
ah
可能更重要的是它们能布局
probably more significant is that they can the layouts
可以改变意外当你更新吗
can change unexpectedly while you're updating the
着色器
shader
它也许不总是直观的
and it's maybe not always intuitive as to how it's
改变下
changed beneath
在表面下
beneath the surface
这可能有点难调试,可以
so it can be a little bit difficult to debug and can
造成很大的挫折
cause a lot of frustration
这是一个机制,你真的应该方法
so this is a mechanism that you really should approach
相当谨慎,更喜欢使用显式的
fairly sparingly and really prefer to use explicit
购买集团布局
buying group layout
嗯
um
我要邮政通过这些最后的几张幻灯片
i'm going to zip through these last few slides really
快速
quick
so we can move on to next
但基本上
but basically
当你宣布嗯的布局信息
whenever you're declaring um the layout of the information
你将进入一个着色器
that you're going to pass into a shader
你用所谓的购买群体布局
you're using something called buying group layout
你可以显式地声明这些或者你
and you can explicitly declare these or you you will
通常只是这些,然后创建显式地声明
usually just explicitly declare these and then create
从这些和购买群体的实际资产
buying groups of the actual assets from those and
这样做的好处是你可以分享
the benefit of doing this is that you can then share
布局之间的多个不同的渲染管道
that layout between multiple different render pipelines
多个渲染状态
multiple render states
呃
uh
这样做它
and by doing it
你在哪里把同一组裁员和相同的槽
where you put same by group layoffs and the same slot
在每一个渲染管道
in every render pipeline
你可以得到一个看起来有点渲染循环
you can get to a render loop that looks a little bit
像这样
like this
在那里我去说
where i go and say
嘿
hey
我有这组共同制服像相机啊
i've got this set of common uniforms like camera ah
未来的度量矩阵视图
prospective matrix view metrics
诸如此类的
stuff like that
,我要把它在我的开始
and i'm just gonna set it once at the beginning of my
渲染循环
render loop
然后其他管道将能够使用它
and then every other pipeline will be able to use it
是哦
as is uh
这是一个大规模的状态量的减少
this is a mass reduction in the amount of state that
你需要设置哦
you need to set uh
特别是当你有这就是共享
especially when you got something that's just shared
之间的一切
between everything
真正的模式,你应该看看
and it's really the pattern that you should be looking
当你试图和提高性能
for when you're trying to improve performance and
通过g p呈现
by g p rendering
这是我们推荐的一大原因
so that's one of the big reasons why we really recommend
你管理自己的布局
that you managed your own uh layout
这就是我今天有时间
and that's all i have time for today
呃
uh
所以非常感谢你
so thank you very much
呃
uh
我要继续哦写信息
i'm going to continue uh writing up information about
最佳实践,将它们放在网上
best practices and publish them online
嗯
um
你将能够找到那些当我发布它们
you'll be able to find those when i publish them at
我的twitter账户哦或者呃的联系我
my twitter account uh or uh the links that i got on this
去年这边
last side here
如果你有问题专门为我
and if you have questions specifically for me
你可以随时给我发邮件在p h l谷歌。com
you can always email me at p h l to google dot com
谢谢你！
thank you
现在,我相信我们会手去解决
and now i believe we're going to hand off to tackle
英雄
hero
是的
yes
非常感谢你
thank you so much
布兰登
brandon
这是神奇的
that was amazing
嗯
um
谢谢你让我们的前缘的全科医生
thanks for keeping us on the leading edge of what gp
发展和展示我们真的不得不使用
developments and showing us really had to use the
p我
a p i well
是的
yeah
这就像一个英雄现在在日本
so it's like a hero is in japan right now
这是一个非常
and it's a a very
对他很疯狂的小时
very crazy hour for him
所以他没能参加他将呃完全和生活
so he wasn't able to attend live and he will be uh perfectly
展示他的在线编辑器摆动
presenting his online wiggle editor
嗨
hi
我说今天从modella
i am talking here from modella today
我想介绍一下我的个人项目在线w g
i want to introduce my personal project online w g
s l编辑哦
s l editor oh
我现在在日本的产假
i'm on parental leave in japan now
所以我事先我录这个视频
so i i recorded this video beforehand
我希望我能加入国内媒体时间
i wish i could join the media at home time
无论如何
anyway
oh w g s l uh
这是一个这是一个新的web g p u脱落语言
it is a it is a new shedding a language for web g p u
没有
no
我希望别人在媒体上已经解释道
i expect uh someone else in the media has already explained
什么
what
所以问题
so question
怎么你想学习一个新的脱落语言
how do you want to study a new shedding language
你不想做实际编写代码
don't you want to do it by actually writing the code
和看到的影响,好消息
and seeing the effects and good news
我做了一个在线w g s l编辑器
i made an online w g s l editor
它是生命编码编辑器
it is life coding editor
您可以测试w g s l
you can test w g s l on it
呃
uh
它运行在您的web浏览器
it runs on your web browsers
你不需要
you don't need to
你不需要安装任何只是访问
you don't need to install anything but just access
网络
the web
呃
uh
编辑web应用程序的页面
the editor web application page
因此,更多的时间。
so the more time.
这是与应用程序页面编辑器
this is editor with application page
如果您将鼠标指针移到窗口
now if you move the mouse pointer into the window
呃
uh
编辑器显示
the editor shows up
如果你搬出来
if you move it out
编辑器是隐藏的,你可以看效果
the editor is hidden and you can watch the effects
更清楚地
more clearly
和编辑器支持嗯基本编辑功能
and the editor supports um basic editor features
审查和
like review and
让我们嗯
so let's uh
让我们先从改变颜色灰色通过编辑
let's start with changing the color to gray by editing
这里的片段的影子
the fragment shadow here
灰色灰色是
the grey grey is
编辑。
edit.
自动编译的代码
the code is automatically compiled
你可以不可以看到灰色的车吗
what is it you can won't you can see the grey car
和编辑器支持空气突出我把
and the editor supports air highlighting let me put
一些错误的代码在这里
some wrong code here
正如你看到的
and as you see
空气核心突出显示和顶部的状态
the air core is highlighted and the status at the top
离开了错误
left became error
如果你点了错误的代码
and if you point the highlighted wrong code
你可以看到代码的原因是错误的
you can you can see the reason why the code is wrong
没有
no
该功能有助于帮助你理解w g s l
this feature helps helps you understand the w g s l
语法
a grammar
编辑器支持一些几何和相机
and the editor supports some geometry and camera
选型
type selection
现在你现在可以测试箱的桌子g m
now you now you can test the desk with the box g m
迭代可以旋转几何几何
iterate that you can rotate the geometry geometry
正确的
right
不仅和片段着色器
and not only the fragment shader
还可以编辑材质为我们播放
but also you can edit the broadcast shader for us
更新哥哥的交易员
update the brother's trader
呃。
uh.
吃了。
eat.
是的。
yeah.
嗯,。
um, for this.
所以改变。
so change.
你。
you.
所以我们申请。
so let's apply.
杂草的成绩。
weed grades.
谢谢你！
thank you.
ya.
演讲者。
speaker.
ya.
迪士尼。
disney.
好的,让我们搬回来。让我们回到幻灯片。
okay, let's move back. let's move back to the slides.
所以未来的工作。
so future works.
目前
currently
编辑器
the editor
因为你只有在chrome上运行
since you run on only on chrome
我们也许与windows
we maybe with windows
我想添加更多的浏览器平台的支持
i want to add more browsers in the platform support
事实上我出售一些反馈到燃烧室
actually  i sell some feedback to the firebox
幸运的是,编辑器将能够运行
luckily  the editor will be able to run
很快。
soon.
我想添加纹理
and i want to add texture
texture support with editor
但是你将能够测试材质编辑器
but you will be able to test textures on the editor
我想支持安全负载叉和
and i'm thinking of supporting safe load fork and
共享的共享代码
share the shared code
所以你将能够分享所以呃你分享记录
so you will be able to share the so uh your share record
与他人
with others
你可以学习哦w g s l从其他他人
and you can learn uh w g s l from the other from others
共享
shared
呃
uh
的最后阶段资源哦
the last phase of resources uh
这是一个存储库
this is a repository
编辑器
the editor
你可以把它扔一个演示
you can throw it a demo
也可以阅读源代码
and also you can read the source code
你的贡献和反馈是非常重要的
your contributions and feedback are very important
和非常受欢迎
and very welcome
现在
now
感谢你的倾听
thank you so much for listening
所以呃
so uh
在这里谢谢垂直谈这个了不起的工具
thank you vertically talk here for this awesome tool
精彩的演示
awesome presentation
嗯
um
每个人都
everybody
I hope that you 'l l learn a wiggle really easily by
i hope that you'll learn a wiggle really easily by
哦玩这个工具
uh playing around with it with this tool
所以呃
so uh
让我们手呃杰米·桑切斯嗯旁边
let's hand off next to uh jamie sanchez um
谁将呃感觉他惊人的工作代码
who will be uh feeling his amazing work on the code
系列号
number series
你好,每个人都能听到我。
hello, can and everyone hear me.
看看我的屏幕
and see my screen
我们可以听到你伟大和看到你的屏幕
we can hear you great and see your screen
好的,很酷。
okay, cool.
所以,是的
so yeah
谢谢你！
thank you
每一个人
everyone
让我我的名字是雅马哈桑切斯
for having me my name is yamaha sanchez
我u我工程师做可视化
i'm u i engineer uh doing visualization at this point
但我确实在黑暗的小时创造困难
but i do create difficulty in the dark hours of the
晚上嗯
night um
我要对我的过程和我解释
and i'm gonna explain about my process and what i've
在
been up to
嗯
um
所以第一个问题是为什么创造性的编码
so in the first question would be why creative coding
也许他们为什么不创造性的编码
and probably they're why not creative coding
所以在某种程度上
so in a way
呃
uh
创造性的编码是是一种释放
creative coding is is quite liberating in the sense
哦没有一定的路线图
that uh there's no necessarily road map
没有交付
there's no deliveries
没有
there are no
好你的
okay yours
嗯
um
你可以设定自己的目标,和,并满足他们
you can set your own goals and and and and meet them
以自己的节奏
at your own pace
嗯
um
你可以设置你的约束
you can set your your constraints
你可以设置你的期望
you can set your expectations
which is is deliberating
它是在同一时间
it's at the same time
这是充实的
it's fulfilling
能够达到有意识或者无意识
being able to reach consciously or unconsciously
嗯或皮尔斯和副有趣的事情
uh or by pierce and deputy interesting things
这也是也是相当好
it's also it's also quite good
它基本上是很有趣
and it's basically it's fun
它真的很有趣
it's it's really fun
所以我要解释我的过程
so i'm going to explain my process
this is not necessarily something that applies to
每一个人
everyone
呃
uh
每个人都有自己的方式处理与网络
everyone has their own way of dealing with with web
发展和和有这样的工具哦
development and and and there are tools um like this
一个适合我
one works for me
不规范的
it's not prescriptive
不应该有任何如何如何
there's not meant to be any any exactly how uh how to
uh
所以使用一个编辑
so use an editor
使用visual studio代码
use visual studio code
我使用一个服务器
i use a server
无论服务器哦
whatever server uh
是什么原因
what's the reason
我的平台
my platform
在这种情况下,python或注意服务器chrome
in this case a python or a note server chrome as
通常像三js框架或库
and usually a framework or library like three js is
真的有用得到很多网站的代码
really useful to get a lot of the website code out of
的方式和关注你可以哦
the way and focus on on what you can actually uh deal
与
with
呃
uh
我不使用n p m
i don't use n p m
我用的包
i use bundles
没有类型三个编译器
no type three compiler
没有生活
no livelihood
一切
everything
我认为它阻碍了
all that i think it gets in the way
但每个人都能给每个人一个流
but everyone can give everyone a flow
所以我有一个结构的方式
so the way the way i have a structure
我通常有一个模板哦哦的复制粘贴
i usually have a template uh with uh with a copy paste
然后我从那里开始
and then i start going from there
这是一个指数h d m l
it's an index h d m l
它有一个主模块,进口一些功能
it's got a main module that imports some functions
已经很好,给我一个渲染场景
that are already fine that give me a render a scene
和角度相机
and perspective camera
我可以调整注册处理程序
i can register resize handlers
我可以注册更新
i can register updates
负载模型环境地图在明年
load models environment maps in next year
我哦
i uh
一些看到了一些,似乎是一个多维数据集实践
some seen some that seems like a cube practice
并从那里
and from there
呃
uh
你可以开始编码
you can start the coding
所以如果你喜欢
so if you ever be like
你从哪里开始
where do you start
他们想要的东西,一旦你得到一个主意
what what they want once you get an idea
所以如果你没有一个主意
so or if you don't have an idea
通常你会发现它很有趣的东西
so usually you would find something that it it's interesting
呃,你想复制或涉及的东西
uh that you wanna replicate or something that comes
或者有些纸
to mind or somewhat paper or something
但有灵感之类的提示
but there's inspiration on on things like prompts
所以这里黄金会员或正确的
so that here's where things like gold member or right
现在
now
1月
january
来
come
对不熟悉的人哦
it's uh for people that are not familiar with this
在一个月
during a month
有一个有一个挑战的东西
there's a there's a challenge of getting something
每天每日的基础上在一个提示
daily based on on on one prompt per day one
一个
one
一个主题可以还有11月搅拌器
one subject you can there's also november for blender
但你可以橙色多佛
but you can be orange dover
这是绘画
which is for painting
但你可以把它
but you can take it
你可以把这些或自己
you can take any of this or come up with your own
嗯
um
还有你可以找到灵感在你的社会
there's also you can find inspirations on your social
媒体提要像instagram哦
media feeds like to your instagram uh
下面我推荐的人不要做你
i recommend following people that don't do what you
通常喜欢插图或游戏开发
usually do like illustration or game development
你从你的地区
something that is out of your your area
嗯
um
这就像给你前进的能量相同
that's like the same energy that give you move forward
有兴趣哦
there's interest uh
嗯你甚至可以像罗斯n f t画廊
there's uh you can even like rose n f t galleries
有一些发现
there's something to be found
在为谷歌图片事件,嗯就像如果你开始
in in that um for google images event like if you start
寻找的东西
searching for something
嗯
um
你可以找到相关的图片
you can find related images
你可以找到有趣的需要在概念上
you can find interesting takes on on on on concepts
数学概念或类似的东西
mathematical concepts or things like that
所以我的方法令人吃惊
so my approach startling
只是去开始做一些模块
just get there started doing something in that modules
和功能你需要它们,因为你不是
and function as you need them uh because you're not
再次试图建立
trying to build again
提到你不试图建立呃呃框架
mentioning you're not trying to build uh uh framework
在理想的情况下
ideally
所以一旦你理解了这个团队
so once you've got that team that
这一目标
that goal
就像去
just like go for it
构建它
build it
呃
uh
随时像我下或删除它
feel free to like me under or drop it
你觉得你在浪费你的时间
you feel like you're wasting your time
其他东西会
something else will come
也许你会发现一些隐藏的黄金,你可以探索
maybe you find some hidden gold that you can explore
那不是你最初打算做什么
that wasn't on what you initially intended to do it
真是太好
it's so good
这就是为什么你的期望只设定的误差
that's why your expectations are set by error only
对你来说
for you to be set
然后
so then
是我多年来的事情
as things that i've been over the years
建筑哦,是有用的
building uh and are useful
比如
so for instance
我呃函数分布的数据
i have uh functions for distribution of data
对于随机噪声
for random noises
嗯嗯你2 d, 3 d l维恩的声音
there's uh uh your two d three d l dimensional uh noises
他们拼写噪音旋度f b女士,您可以使用
they're spelling noise curl f b ms that you can use
它是一件好事c p u g p u实现
it's it's a good thing to have a c p u and a g p u implementation
所以你可以像开关迅速,您想要使用
so you can like switch quickly where you want to use
他们
them
嗯是抽样
uh was on this sampling
是有用的分发
it's useful to distribute things
我们真的这些都是斐波那契螺旋
our fibonacci spirals into the really all these are
货物
the goods
位置的初始结构
placement of your initial structure that are not
在这种情况下只是随机的哦
just random uh in this case
例如
for instance
这基本上就是实例化后哦哦
this is basically instancing uh following uh one
这些人实际上螺旋三维
of these people actually spiral on three d
它使用呃一堆长矛
and it uses uh a bunch of spears
颜色是担心机会
and the color is worried about chances
所以这可能是像等离子体材质的玩具
so this could be like one of those shader toy plasmas
只是它发生在这样的蛇
it's just that it's happening in this kind of snake
它
it
所以如果几何图形担心
so if geometries worried
什么像你想要探索创造性
what like you want to be exploring creatively
有很多的方法来做
there's many ways of doing
你可以得到程序的方式就像撞三角形
you can get procedurally like just bumping triangles
和脸
and faces
您可以使用呃游行广场或多维数据集
you can use uh marching squares or marching cubes
对我国
to our country
呃
uh
无论你想实现在c p u或g p u嗯嗯
whatever you want to implement uh on c p u or g p u um
您可以使用s d f信号距离
you can use s d f signal distance
未能创建你的你的你的结构
fails to create your your your your structures
和隐式函数
and implicit functions
这一个,例如,就像,呃创建。
this one, for instance, was about like, uh creating.
这些是员工函数的函数
these are functions that employees functions that
两个物体扭曲通过s d f和宏伟吗
are distorted through s d f and grandeur two objects
我们正在行进中的多维数据集
we are marching cubes
这就是整件事情
that was the the whole thing
只是有一些光
just had some light
一些材料
some material
它看起来不错
and it looks nice
嗯
um
如果你想去剃须
if you want to go for shaving
例如
for instance
嗯
um
没有需要准确的或物理
there's no need to be accurate or physical
b b r
there's b b r
这是很高兴
it's it's nice
你可以用它
you can use it
但是没有没有不一定
but there's no there's no it's not necessarily there
和创造性,有点艺术
and being creatively and a bit artsy
你可以做任何事
you can do anything
兰伯特的经典的骨头吗
have lambert go for the classic bones
百叶窗和任何你想要的
blinds and anything you want
化妆真的很有用
makeup are really useful
这种色调的垂直的地图吗
are this kind of of of shades vertical maps that
如果你呃呃闪电闪电非常低廉
that if you uh lightning lightning very cheaply uh
你可以使用f f x储蓄
you can use the f f x on your saving
您可以使用属性
you can use the property
我知道我在污染
i know i'm in a pollution
以外的任何可能有点复杂
anything that might be a bit complicated outside
of the a geometry
你可以用你可以尝试实现非逼真
you can use you can try to achieve non photorealistic
渲染优化剃须草图
rendering tune shaving sketch
你可以在这个很有创意
you can be very creative in in this
一旦你得到你想要的东西来呈现
once you get something that you want to render
还有方便的有几个
then there's there's it's convenient to have several
渲染库函数
render libraries functions
所以在这种情况下
so in this case
例如
for instance
呃
uh
粒子或指出供应商真的很有用
particles or point out vendors are really useful
甚至像我们作为你的价值
even like us as as the value of what do you have
嗯像屏幕空间投影或网格线
uh or mesh lines which are like screen space projected
行
lines
所以他们更厚比常规的厚
so they're thicker they can be thicker than the regular
呃web g l线
uh web g l lines
或在这种情况下
or in this case
有一个默认的是基于散射
there's a default lines were based on scattering
点和积累或几帧
the dots and accumulating or a few frames
这让这种耳语
so it gives this this kind of whisper
吸烟。
smoking it.
效果哦
effect uh
一个品牌,现在我们有三种材质和体积
a volume branded now that we have three textures and
流在你做什么材质
flow textures in what you do
我们可以做哦
and we can do uh
呃
uh
很多东西也是真的
a lot of stuff is also really
为调试非常有用哦不管你正在做的事情
really useful uh for debugging whatever you are doing
甚至像建筑哦我们正如我们看到的东西
or even for like building uh something as we as we see
基本上哦
which basically uh
嗯
um
东西非常的队列
something else is very much inside the queue for the
球体呃三个探测器或悉尼的业务
sphere uh over a three detector or a sydney business
建筑
building
后期处理是一件大事,你也可以做
post processing is a big thing that you can also do
有很多事情你可以做
there's there's so many things that you can do there
它基本上是当你结束你的渲染
and it's basically when you get to the end of your render
你有这样的感觉
and you feel like that
错过一些打孔
it misses some punch
呃
uh
它很方便找到
it's it's it's convenient to like find something
我应该像
like should i like
提高水平
boost the levels
我喜欢紧缩白人和基本上可以吗
could i like crunch the the whites and basically just
去在photoshop中,你可能会做
go for the equivalent that you would might do in photoshop
寻找方程哦
look for the equation uh
通常在网上实现和
which are usually online and just implemented and
添加到您的工具集组成一个接一个的繁荣
added to your tool set one after the other boom composition
冠状病毒和你一样当你提升操作
coronavirus promoted operations as as you as you
找到他们
find them
或许有一件事是真的实现
maybe one thing is literally implemented
桶形失真,或转变
the barrel distortion and or the shift
去的。
and go with that.
所以最后
so finally
一些新的交易
some new deals
呃
uh
比如物理放松
things like physics for relaxation
因为这个原因
for this reason
东西也非常有用
things is also really useful
呃
uh
你可以顺利创建的措施
you can you can smooth measures that you create out
一个匹配的数据集等等
of a matching cubes and things like that
你继续寻找你需要的东西,也许
you just keep finding things that you need and maybe
找到如何如何实现它们
find how to how to implement them
嗯
um
这基本上是一个粒子系统品牌
this is basically a particle system branded with
实例化之前,光和材料
instancing and the before the light and materials
从三个j s阴影通过,您可以使用
from three j s shadow passes that you can use for for
生成
generating
像我提供材质
like uh i provide the shader
我可以得到一个帧缓冲吗
can i get a frame buffer
就是这样
that's it
就像一个着色器,我可以使用嗯喂地图
it's like a shader that i can use uh to feed the maps
嗯我一切的影子传递管道
of everything else uh on my pipeline shadow passes
postperson或乒乓球传入你想要的结果
for postperson or ping pong passes in case you want
做一些g p g p o
to do some g p g p o
你需要像用在来回
and you need to like write in in the back and forth on
相同的方法
the same method
这是不允许的
which is not allowed
所以你从一个另一个条目的方法
so you go from one method to the other entry
嗯
um
所以当我使用的工具
so when for tools that i use
我使用这个工具为了像响应模式
i use the tool responsive mode in order to like
需要解决和处理我想看到哦
take the resolution and handle what i want to see uh
我用我的捕捉校园chrome扩展得到
i use my capture campus chrome extension to get the
呃快照和g, g的顶部
uh snapshot and have a gigabyte and gigabyte top of
我我所做的步骤
steps of my what i do
我用来捕捉g s捕捉逐帧动画
i used to capture g s to capture frame by frame animations
和事件像时不时b o年代快速输出
and events like every now and then o b s for a quick output
所以说到具体的例子哦
so speaking of specific examples uh
这是提示冷供应商叫吸引力
this is uh the prompt for cold vendor was called attraction
而不是你在做经典的珊瑚噪音
and instead of you doing the classical coral noise
我想重温你提供的东西
i wanted to revisit something that you offer
让我们回去。
let's go back.
我就去哦
i will go uh
东西没用哦天是静电
something that didn't work uh back in day was was electrostatic
呃收山
the charge uh charge hills
所以,嗯
so um
因为它是一个端到端问题
since it's an end to end problem
这有点太贵为仿真计算哦
it's a bit too expensive to calculate uh for the simulation
这是三个探测器变现
so it's cashed in a three detector
然后推到的
and then it's pushed to the to the
材质和中移动鼠标
to the shader and the charge that is moved in the mouse
可以计算着色器,因为它是
that can be calculated in the shader because it's
一两米
one two m
这是负担得起的主题
which is uh affordable theme
我可以停止这个聚会哦
can i stop this party uh
这是一个g.b。gpu模拟与粒子
so it's a g.b.gpu simulation with with particles
在生活中有位置和速度和质量
that have a position in life and velocity and mass
他们只是在这些他们就像追踪
and they just they're just like traced across these
字段
fields
你可以随机
and you can randomize
这基本上,你看到的是积累
and this that you're seeing is basically the accumulation
粒子的哦
of particles uh
有一个随机生成和梯度
there's a gradient that is randomly generated and
通过材质作为两个检测器
pass the to the shader as a two detector
得到亿万富翁位置的盒子
so you get billionaire position out of box
最后,一些。
and finally, some.
盛开在这戏剧性的操作比如发光效果
blooming for like glow effect in this dramatic operation
呃
uh
另一个例子是这块石头
another example is this stone
促进石
the promote stone
石头本身是生成与单哦
so the the stone itself is generated uh with single
距离字段和扭曲
distance fields and distortions
所以这。
and so this.
嗯
um
有噪音的借贷支付这具体
there's borrowing noise to pay this concretely a
表面呃f b m的两个分离和委员会
surface uh f b m's commission of two separations and
这是计算的
it's calculated ones
它挠在一分之一质感哦
and it's scratched in a in a texture uh
所以它可以
so it can be it
每次都是更昂贵的
it is more expensive to do every time
基本上和过程生成的表面
and the process basically generates the the surface
密码
password
有数学的差距和法人团体的一员和环形照明
has the math gap and the corporator and the ring lighting
法线和位置为了体积
and the normals and positions in order for the volume
渲染
render
三3月到三维燃烧噪音和获得
just three march into a three d burning noise and get
这些内部
these interior
就像闪闪发光的
which is like shimmering
这是最后一个
and there's a final
通过结合所有
pass that combines everything
这是一个开花和post和一切
and that's a bit of bloom and post and everything
所以你可以看到喜欢的不同
so you can see like the the different
挡泥板的影响
effects of the mudguard
这里有一个霜因素
there's there's like a frost factor
这使得它更少啊
which makes it less ah
祝福
blessing
呃
uh
最后
and finally
从昨天
from yesterday
p r n g
there's the p r n g
这是哦
which is uh
是可视化呃随机所有这些工作
it was about visualizing uh random all this work
right
好吧
okay
嗯
um
这赛车像随机分布的数字
this racing like random distribution of numbers
然后消息实例信息的分布
so then message of instance messages are distributed
用毒药
with a poison
this sampling over here
放松一点
relax the bit
所以他们不重叠
so they don't overlap
模具模型是一个g l t f模型和它的使用多渲染
the die model is a g l t f model and it's using multi render
这些目标筛选接种
target for these screening space of inoculation
这是非常好的,我们可以换一个吗
which is really nice that we can do that in one
零
zero
两个
two
呃
uh
它是利用多示例渲染目标
it's using multi sample to render targets for the
color pass you get uh smooth image
and you don't need to use f x a a or any other processing
嗯。
um.
是嗯和组合
and the combination is the um
屏幕空间
the screen space
类似的问题这嗯嗯阴影,不错
similar question that's this uh nice um shadows and
全球消除的
and kind of global elimination
+常规3 g s浅滩呃结合一切
plus the regular three g s shallows uh combine everything
成一个最终的价格处理
into one final price of processing
嗯
um
所以
so
是的
yeah
这是我做的,尽管在twitter上这个我哦
that's that's me done despite on twitter uh this my
github
有很多东西我的百分之九十
there's a bunch of stuff like ninety percent of my
代码
code
有东西释放我的网站啊
is there a thing to release my website uh
如果你有任何问题或任何如何开始
and if you have any questions or any how to get started
或任何帮助
or any help
啊
ah
只是
just
不要犹豫的问你。谢谢你！
don't hesitate to ask you. thank you.
感谢你你的工作表现
thank you so much for your job for presenting your
你的过程
your process
你的工作是令人惊异的
your work is just amazing
你是一个灵感的
you're an inspiration to all of
谢谢你！
thank you.
嗯。
so um.
呃。
uh.
好吧
well
遵循
to follow
遵循这惊人的表现
to follow that amazing presentation
我们有什么我肯定会是另一个令人惊异的
and we have what i'm sure is gonna be another amazing
one from donald vintage instrument play canvas uh
talking about the latest rendering techniques
so donovan
thanks for presenting in advance
and please take it away
thanks so much, kevin.
um
hopefully
you can uh
you can all hear me
ah
so yeah
my name is donovan
and i'll be giving a quick update from the play campus
for those of you who may not know
uh
take campus is a three d content creation platform
for the web
which comprises a set of tools
we have a fully collaborative browser based editor
an open source model viewer
a night based shader editor and
and open source runtime and
um
not users are generally interested in creating games
vr content
visualizes and e commerce
and they want to run these across the broadest range
of hardware possible uh
so they wanted to run on desktop
mobile and the web g l one and two
and so over the last year
we've continued to develop our engineering tools
in particular to address some of the demands of the
company
uh
we find that uh brands like cartier here
you know they require photo realism in order to maximize
the online sales conversions
and of course
they want their products to look amazing
but they also want their users to have the best possible
experience
so you know
this means that they they want fast
low times and smooth rendering uh
and so today
i'll be getting over some of the improvements we've
made in the engine um to meet some of these demands
so first up is clustered lighting
well
what is that
it's a solution for rendering lots of dynamic lights
in real time uh
it's often been combined with uh deferred shading
uh and has been used uh to great effect on trouble
a titles like doomed uh and many others
the engine itself is the forward render where we generate
shades of drawn time by combining together chunks
of code
and in our old lighting method
lights would be baked into the shade of code directly
meaning when when lights were added or removed from
the scene
changes needed to rebuild
and this approach
while relatively straightforward
did come with a bunch of limitations uh
it was slow to to render lots of lights in the scene
because uh
you know
all surfaces were evaluating all lights um
we had unpredictable resource usage
sometimes running out of uniforms and samples
um and in in game trade compilation was also a challenge
for our users
ah
so in order to address some of these limitations
uh
we've been implementing trusted lighting um
so how does it work
well
there are basically uh three steps
uh in step one, given a set of lights.
we uh we constructed three d grid covering the lights
uh in world space
and then on cpu for each for each cell on the grid
we calculate the intersecting light
and we store their indices mapped to some location
on a two d texture
and uh
this texture
we call the uh the trusted
uh
then instead
two
we store the lighting parameters themselves
that is
uh the lights
position
rotation
color
etc
and we encode the parameters into the light buffer
which itself is just another two d text joint
and then finally
in step three
we rendered the scene using the two generated textures
uh and for each pixel from the fragments world space
position uh
we can get the the the cluster grid cell uh and loop
over the the light indices
we can read the parameters from the light buffer
and using these
we can calculate the lighting contribution um and
next
we can actually take a look at this uh in action
so so yeah
here we have a scene with a single moving light
we can overlay on top of that the cluster grid to see
its extensions
you see it move along with the light.
we can also add more lights and see that the plastic
grid is resized to encompass them all uh at the top
left there
you can see the light buffer being updated with new
lighting parameters
um
the light positions are the ones twinkling
them top left and bottom left
you can see the cluster grid with a changing light
industries
um with clustered lighting
though
the story doesn't end there uh shadow offers and cookies
are uh uh not able to be handled in the in in the usual
manner because uh web yielders and support the summer
uh rate indexing
so we also added dynamic texture edison uh
which packs the shadow maps and the cookies into the
texture at us at the front lights uh closer to the viewer
will be assigned larger areas of the atlas and lights
further away small area
um
the winds frost over the previous lighting method
are pretty substantial
we can now add lights to the scene of that performance
issues
we have predictable resource usage uh since all like
data is encoded into these two textures instead of
what we had before
where you know textures
um
sorry shares were using their varying numbers of
uh uniforms and samples um
and we now experience fewer shady comparison from
time and looking to the future
uh
we plan to migrate completely to the cluster solution
we want to investigate cheap decal rendering using
a similar method to this uh and also uh investigate
some of volumetric writing solutions
so moving on
we've also been working on our uh image based lighting
uh
our previous method required multiple rendering
parts based on the granton hardware uh
if the device had no texture
other d support uh
which is a spiritual money can do for evolute uh map
otherwise
if the device supported fewer than sixteen samples
uh
we'd render using a single cube map with the roughness
uh stored in the makeup
otherwise uh with sample from six individual uh cute
maps
each containing a reference level one
and so
of course
the downsides of this approach
again
we had varying resource usage um on the runtime
depending on the runtime advice
um
the lighting of the different depending on the hardware
support uh
and we had complex code pass to maintain seamless
edge filtering was difficult with mud maps as well
so uh we implemented a new method
which packs the lighting data onto us onto a uh a two
detector at us uh instead
so here's an example at least as you can see
uh
we use a rectangular projection for that
down the left  we store the reference pyramid
uh
down the right
we stole the usual environment magnet chain um
and in the sense that we've also we also got the prefilled
today
when it comes to rendering surfaces with blurry reflections
we manually blend two levels of the blurry pyramid
based on surface roughness
on surfaces with sharp reflections
we use an extra tap to sample the ah
the sharp map pyramid um
but this time using uh texture derivatives
what this means is that uh with three taps
we get very reflections and filtered sharp reflections
um
the sharp reflections being most prone to
so for example, ah, on this chess piece.
with sharp refractions actually uh the image top
uh top right uses one tap and below it
uh and of course
under movement
the additional filtering helps to reduce twinkles
uh
we've also updated our pre filtering to be more in
line with the industry standards
so instead of fund
we are using g g x uh
we generate this uh using important sampling
which actually means we're approaching real time
speeds for generating pre filtered environments
uh
i also want to give a quick shut up to the uh the excellent
chronos sample viewer source code um
it's been invaluable um a for us um implementing our
own image based
uh
so yeah
in summary
we've updated our ideal rendering to have consistent
resource usage and performance
and to look at the same across our yeah
multiple devices
we actually have a set of online examples demonstrating
you know
these techniques and more
there's a live coating panel on there
and you can try it out yourself if you're interested
uh with the address on screen
please take a look
um
the engine itself uh is also available on github under
mit license
um
and that's
that's all for me
i just like to send a shout out to uh to the autumn play
campus team and especially martin
who uh implemented the custom lighting we saw today
uh
also we're hiring
so yeah
please reach out
if you
thanks so much for listening.
thank you so much
donovan
for presenting uh your and the team's amazing work
here
uh
i'm just i'm just blown away
i mean
you've done amazing work to get around hardware and
specification limitations and just bring leading
edge lighting solutions to the engines of the web
so just fantastic
okay
so with that
let's go to the q and a uh and let me encourage everyone
here uh to please join the web
g l and web g p online communities because i see some
really great questions here that could be answered
uh on a faster cadence than once every three months
which is roughly when we're holding these online
beat ups
and we'd love to
you know
get you the information that you need hear from you
more often
so shall we uh go through the q and a.
i don't know if anybody from the chronoscope wants
to put on an interstitial slide
and i'll i guess
turn on my video
hopes no host to stop the video
that's fine
okay
so all of the presenters
please uh be ready to answer questions
let's go down them uh in chronological orders
so ron bush
nick asks
will the browser be able to manipulate an important
export compressed textures like we can do today with
images
would anyone like to pick
sure, i can take it.
um.
we're not planning any functionality to compress
these textures in the browser compression
i think somebody actually mentioned this in the chat
but compression is generally a very expensive process
that's done ahead of time in order to get optimal quality
um
we are considering at some point
potentially um adding sport to the browser for decoding
these compressed images
but right now
we don't have anything planned yet
so right now
you need to use ah
use a library
in order to decompress.
uh
you can press your textures and you can do that
you can do compression in the browser as well
with the weather
some blue library
but it's not very highly recommended because it won't
perform well on
especially in mobile devices
yeah.
so sounds great
thanks for the answer
kai
and i'll mark that one is
as an answer.
okay
uh
going down uh
an anonymous attendee says the recommendations
published on the web g l two pages
yes
i recommend that
but i was fifteen
adoption is only seventy two percent for devices
from the last four years is dropping web gl relevance
in this case
so i'll um
i'll say it completely dropping webgl one support
is
of course
an aspirational goal
and and i hope to get there
you know
in in my lifetime
um
but uh
just keep in mind that the ios adoption curve is is
quite steep
and you know
in the in the limit
um
it's quite good
uh
you may know that like any any android ecosystem where
there's a wide proliferation of devices
um
you know
getting to getting everyone's the latest operating
system takes quite a long time
but the ios ecosystem is difference
and
um, i, i do expect that within.
you know
a few more months that adoption will be even higher
than seventy two percent
so what i would like to encourage once again is get
your pages ready for web gl to you know
do the upgrades
um
you know
taken to account the relatively minor spec differences
between web jill two spec and the uh web jail one extensions
for the same functionality and and get ready to deploy
it um and and put it out there
and when web g o t is available
you know
go for it
and if you have any any metrics in your own app once
you've gotten
you know to the adoption curve that you would like
to see
you can just need to deprecate and remove the old curve
path to simplify your your own app of your own engine
so um
please do uh have a night toward that
that goal
and also
please do try web g.p.u.web g p u
we're aiming for really good market penetration
of the a.p.i.um and uh
and we would like you to get on the leading edge
get compute faders into your apps and start doing
it now
can i add one thing to that really quick can please
please
which is with one g l two uh
one of the best things that you can do if you want to
get ready for web g.p.u.
but aren't quite ready to jump in and and start converting
large chunks of eco based over
he started taking advantage of some of the features
that are available through web g.p.u.
especially uh uniform buffer objects because that
will prepare the structure of your code much better
to switch over to the structure that is required by
web gpu
so highly
great advice
uh
yeah
getting off the uh
you know
jail uniform three f v calls and instead packing your
data into uniform buffers is a a great first step
okay
let's see here
uh ashley golden
high ash uh asks if we want to download pink and j pick
for the smaller file size and then load in a compressed
texture
what's the suggested way
i would like to refuse the suggestion that jpegs and
p.and g's are going to be smaller than the compressed
texture
um
if you are just taking like a raw g x t file or something
like that
yeah
it will probably come out bigger than the jpeg
but if you're using one of the newer super competitive
texture formats like basis universal in a t x two wrapper
or something like that
ah
i find that they frequently match or are better than
the j type file sizes and then transcode into something
of course
is smaller on the g p u as well
so um
there's again
there's we'd really love people to start fully embracing
uh compressed textures all the way through the pipeline
and that includes over the wire because it can be equivalent
or smaller to the assets that you're delivering
okay, super.
uh
i would have said the same thing
good
good heads are brand
okay
let's see
alex short tasks i've experienced a lot of issues
using drako compression that ios has party about
a year ago that scared me off from draycott
so any truth to this concern was likely an implementation
area
so um
first of all
it's it was almost fully above
um
you know
the secretary
ah
itself made it it does things like quantized vertices
and uses maybe
maybe slightly strange um vertex formats
it'll reorganize or draw calls for efficiency
batch them
but i mean
underlying
it's using the same drawing primitives like drawing
and it's drawing rays that you would be using in your
in your engine anyway
so i would like to suggest
first of all
the implementation in on ios is uh is different now
than it was a year ago
so please try the new uh ios fifth sort of the new safari
fifteen and ios
um
second
if you do see any weird issues in your models getting
corrupted
please produce a test case and file a bug
i mean
even if it like
renders correct me on desktop and renders incorrectly
on mobile
i'm sure that we can debug it from that
or even if it's just you could just get the wrong examples
wrong rendering
please fix
we'll we'll take a look
please try again
please do report the issues that you see
file bugs
email the webgl depth
let's just get a test case out there
we'll figure out what's going wrong
can we want to make this kind of content work and make
your models
okay
let's see uh the next one
anonymous attendee asks
is using blog to load textures also recommended for
web g
uh, yes.
um
basically
it is the most optimal way to get it something into
an image bit map
and you can use image bit maps
load web g l
they're uh more optimal than going straight from
an image element
and so yes
that that same code path that i presented ah works
equally well for webgl and web gpu
you just swap out what the texture function is at the
end of
yeah, i want to also add that um.
you can use image remaps on workers.
html image element is not available on workers because
it's part of the dom
um
so if you're if you want to be able to move code to a worker
then using image bit map through a blob is highly recommended
sorry, great answers, everybody.
okay
let's see
marco figaro asks the web g l d bug tools are really
cool
that's right
the web g p u d bug tools are really cool
our depth tools for profiling
wiggle shaders planned i've always wanted an easier
way to find a bottlenecks
um
yes
this is an excellent question
we do not have a
actively have plans to work on this yet
but we have dreams um
one way of potentially doing this is to use native
platform debugging tools
we haven't worked like we don't have a lot of experience
with this
but some some native uh some native graphics debugging
tools can be attached to the web browser to a web browser
to debug what's going on inside of the web page
so for example
x code or uh or microsoft's picks debugger
i don't know which of these configurations work
i don't know exactly how to get them set up
but people have had success with them
um
the native debug tools generally are going to give
you a richer debugging experience because they can
hook directly into the uh into like vendor specific
debugging functionality uh that we wouldn't be able
to use in the browser um
but we do have ideas about
for example
running shaders uh in software using using our software
render and and allowing debugging through that
but we have no plans yet to do anything like that
it's sort of an open research project
yeah
this is a great topic
i would definitely encourage you to post this to the
uh the web g p u community group and and ask because
you know every browser is gonna need to handle this
a little bit differently
uh
i think it's probably like an intractable problem
for the browsers to subsume the functionality of
these native profilings rules
so infrastructure
i think is the direction we want to take um
and you know
using the best to breed
native profilers that are out there
uh
we we want to enable that better on the web for web g.p.u.uh
than than we did in the web gl ecosystem
okay
going on the yangtze asks
is there a recommended format for float textures
and web g o two and web g p u um young also later was asking
uh
i don't see the question anymore
but i think he's basically asking whether there's
a recommended file format for importing these
so a couple of points here
i'll make the point about the
the actual internal format for these uh
we actually invested quite a bit of time during the
development of web g o two for safari and re specifying
uh floating point texture and durability
so the universally available format is half float
our red r sixteen f r g sixteen f and r g b a sixteen f that's
the format you should target
if it has the precision in the range that is suitable
for your application
it's basically available as a renderable format
everywhere
so you can you know
sample from it
you can render to it ping pong back and forth
this is how you can do uh g p g p u and other um techniques
that require floating point data in web g l two and
get them working
for example on a i o s
where only floating point sixteen textures are renderable
thirty two bit textures are not renderable
so that's uh what i would say about the runtime format
now in terms of bringing in
for example
h d r textures um into flow texture
you know from files into flow textures
i'd like to ask the other panelists for opinions on
um, yeah, so.
this is something that's high bit depth images is
something that's sort of been on our radar for a while
so for example
sixteen bit p n g um doesn't have much browser support
uh right now
i think if you want to say bring in a sixteen bit p n g
uh into application
you probably need to use the software decoder like
what assembly of p n g decoder
which is unfortunate um or you can compress your image
data in some other way
so that you get it as a linear buffer and upload that
directly as raw data and
um.
we it's on our radar to have some browser support for
this
so both um
both web gpu and webgl have considered sixteen bit
input um
but there's the
webgl extension is still under draft
and i don't know um
if i i don't
i don't think there's active development development
on it right now
web g p u is planning on doing this later
sometimes after one point oh
because it it's not necessary
it's not required for future priority
but basically um
but it's something we would like to do
so it's an issue that we have tracked for high bit depth
and but um
but it's not not figured out
i don't know if
say like basis
for example
basis universal
has a support for high bit depth
i don't think it does
but there might be
there might be some higher bit depth support in the
in the hdr profiles
i just don't remember if it has support for hdr profiles
of a s t c
um
and we don't support the hdr profiles of a of a s g c
i believe
at least not in web gpu
right now.
so you would have to software decode this.
yeah
so at that point
i mean
i think you could use uh r g b e
you know
r g b plus exponents or go to the full blown open e x r
and software decode that, i mean.
these are gonna be larger files for sure uh both over
the wire and in memory representation
but um
i mean
if you need it
you know you can get the full precision range that
you need
anyway
thanks for the great question
i will say that we answered this live and again
please feel free to reach out to the uh the online discussion
groups of bad questions like this
we'd love to help answer them um
and i i bet you that alexey kenya is from the uh k t x working
group that chronos would love to talk about basis
universal and
okay.
a large bond asks
what is the state of using web g p u through and script
and using c n c plus plus
can we use the regular vulcan c a p i here
um
unfortunately not uh
so we we have a uh sea header for web g p u
which um is not fully fleshed out yet
but it's a shared header between our uh google implementation
missiles implementation um
ultimately
they will be interoperable
so you'll be able to swap out the shared library underneath
the header
um
that is a c a p i uh
and we have c plus plus findings on top of that uh
that header is also available in an inscription
so right now
the header implemented in the script and should be
compatible with the header implemented in dawn
mostly um and mostly compatible with with with what's
implemented in w g p u as well
um
there is no implementation of the vulcan c a p i on top
of web gpu
as far as i'm aware
this is a project that i think would benefit the community
and a lot of people would like to have um
but unfortunately
i'm not aware of anybody who's actually started developing
someday i think someone will.
good stuff
guy
thanks
and what's my favorite one
okay
next question
uh georgia
nicholas asks brendan what would be a good way to reuse
the rendering pipelines from mesh with the same buffer
inputs
and characteristically
the output render target topology
he wants to keep a pool of created pipelines and find
one
you know
looking it up
if it matches
the new input doesn't wanna manage uids manually
just what's the group and based on inputs states
okay
so first
i need to send personal apologies to geology because
i have had this question in my personal inbox for months
now
and a half type reply because it's it's a complex question
and i apologize for not getting back to you on that
thank you for bringing it up here
this is actually a topic that i wanted to cover in my
slides today
but it turns out that i just could not do it justice
in the time that we had um
unless i want to make my entire presentation about
that
but it
topic that i think a lot of people will run into
and so i'm going to be taking the half type response
to you and turning it into a community asset um that
i post along some of the other best practices that
i've done
uh
one tip that i can give you until i'm able to look at
that is
i do a lot of work towards this in the demos that i posted
today
uh
especially like in bookie ball
there's a lot of work that goes into minimizing the
number of pipelines that are created
so you can go spoiling through that code to get some
ideas uh
and then in the meantime
i will be working on some assets to help other people
in the community
uh
figure this out as well because it's probably going
to be one of the primary challenges for new developers
starting up with web g p u and wanting to get some better
performance out of it
okay, great stuff.
georgia also asks
are there any other any plans on supporting pre processors
and pixel
to my knowledge
no
i do once again in my code
have a little snippet of something that handles some
pre processors
uh
i know the kinds development as well
i've seen a few other sprinkled around in the community
so there are
ways to do this that are relatively low
impact
the code for them is usually not very big
but i don't think that we're planning on having a canonical
preprocessor um system in wiggle
yeah
that's right
right now
we're not we're not planning to include a preprocessor
in wiggle
um
i do recommend that you use things like template macros
uh or template strings in javascript um or other templating
engines or whatever uh
whatever you find useful
yeah
you know
in order to add post processing on top of wiggle on
top of wiggle um
i'm sure that there will be lots of projects over time
for implementing some some some form of preprocessor
on top of wiggle
so keep an eye out.
yeah
i i will say that if you just use javascript built in
uh template literals
that gets you most of the way there
it doesn't handle things like if deaths
but um
in terms of just like wanting to replace a particular
symbol with a value
you can do most of that with javascript today with
with no additional libraries needed
and and a lot of us code in the wizard innovation
and stuff
believe it or not
we are starting to run low on time
so let's try to maybe hit some of the top questions
here
um
alexander
i'm gonna defer your question
i'm afraid i don't quite understand what you mean
by web g p compression
i i think that uh the the general answer to this is
yes
any of the compression methods that we're using for
the i.osha and program g.p.u.also by y g l
okay, good stuff, great answer.
okay
uh
stephen
off the doll asks any word community three d and when
they'll start looking into a web gpu implementation
and
uh.
we we have great partnerships with the unity folks
uh and have been discussing this with them for a long
time
we can't pronounce anything on their behalf
but stay tuned
okay
uh
let's see andy ray is asking about a job
he's written a job for jail as a compiler and seeing
the greater place for web g.p.u.
he's suspected to be obsolete for j s users
have a p i access to browser with g p g p compilers in
the produced a s t s
uh
so i'm just gonna venture and say
no
we won't be supporting uh abstract syntax trees
you know
api's for the shaders
um.
on the other hand
wiggle
i would like to say is a uh
it's a clean cut language
that was
you know
based on spear v
primitives at the bottom
so it should be more easily ah possible a bit more regular
perhaps than some of the legacy glsl constructs
and hopefully easier to work with
and we definitely want to have bridges back to the
glsl ecosystem in in many ways
and i suspect anti that your uh previous compiler
will actually have a new legs given the new filter
ecosystem
the ability to maybe output wigs left the bottom level
any other feedback.
okay.
what's called i've done.
uh
let's see
one tabao asks our three detector is going to be supported
on what g p l g l two
yeah.
they work, they they work today in both of them.
yes, okay.
let's see
uh
lens and humphreys asks
has there been any planner discussion of web gpu implement
explicit multi-gpu like there is in vulcan and direct
x twelve